Register of the Paul Jacob papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Paul Jacob papers
1944-1991
90036
Hoover Institution Archives
19 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes (10.6 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, press releases, campaign literature, serial issues, clippings, and memorabilia relating to activities of the Libertarian Party in the United States, its efforts to secure positions on the ballot for its candidates in various states, its opposition to military draft registration, and the trial and imprisonment of Paul Jacob in 1985 for refusal to register for the draft.
Jacob, Paul, 1960-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1990.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1960 Born
1978 Formed campus chapter of Libertarian Party, Westminster College, Missouri
1981 Elected Chairman of the Libertarian Party of Arkansas
1981 Recieved draft registration letter from the Selective Service System
1981 Refused to register and left Arkansas to go underground
1982 Traveled the United States speaking to students and youth about refusing to register
1982 Indicted by grand jury for failure to register for the draft
1984 Arrested by the FBI and sentenced to 5 years in prison
1985 July 2 Entered prison
1985 November 25 Released from prison
1986 Director of Sales, CATO
1987-1988 Director, National Libertarian Party
1988-1989 National Coordinator, Ballot Access Committee
1990 Campaign Manager, Tax Accountability Amendment Committee
Scope and Content of Collection
The Paul Jacob papers consist of writings, correspondence, press releases, campaign literature, serial issues, clippings, and memorabilia relating to activities of the Libertarian Party in the United States, its efforts to secure positions on the ballot for its candidates in various states, its opposition to military draft registration, and the trial and imprisonment of Paul Jacob in 1985 for refusal to register for the draft. Personal correspondence, speeches, writings, clippings, and memorabilia of Jacob are also included.
The majority of the material focuses on Jacob’s draft registration resistance. Jacob traveled the United States during the early 1980s, making his anti-draft registration opinions known in speeches at Libertarian Party and non-Libertarian Party events, letters to the editors of various publication, by creating the anti-draft organization Volunteers for America, publishing the anti-war magazine Scream!, and writing an afterword published in the book The Rainbow Cadenza. Published and unpublished articles and related notes can be found in the Speeches and Writings series, while material relating to the organizations Jacob participated in can be found in the Office Files series.
In addition, Jacob held many prominent roles in the Libertarian Party throughout the 1980s. Materials such as internal memoranda, reports, notes, and printed material relating to his time as the Chairman of Arkansas, National Director, National Ballot Access Coordinator, and his time serving on the National Committee can be found in the Office Files series. Additional Libertarian Party printed material can be found in the Printed Material series.
Libertarianism--United States.; Libertarian Party.; Draft--United States.; Draft registration--United States.; Free enterprise.
- Biographical File, 1979-1991
  Scope and Contents note
  Agendas, awards, short biographies, poems, and printed materials mentioning Paul Jacob. Also includes material relating to Jacob’s arrest, court proceedings, and time spent in prison. Arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Agendas, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Awards, 1980-1988 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - CATO summer seminar notes, 1982 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Clippings, undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Clippings, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Clippings, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Clippings, 1985 (Box-folder 1: 7-8)
  - Clippings, 1985 (Box-folder 19: 1)
  - Clippings, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Clippings, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Court records, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Flyers, 1985-1990, undated (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Jail records, 1980-1985 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - National Speakers Association printed material, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - News releases, undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Photographs, 1989, undated (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Poems, undated (Box-folder 2: 5-6)
  - Poems, 1979-1983 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Posters, 1983-1985, undated (Box-folder 19: 2)
  - Probation records, 1985-1990 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Short biographies, 1985-1989, undated (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Student records, 1980-1989 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Underground ID, 1984-1985, undated (Box-folder 2: 11)
- Correspondence, 1978-1991, undated
  Letters sent and received by Paul Jacob while in prison. Also includes correspondence with various Libertarian Party committees, the Paul Jacob Defense Fund, the Selective Service System, Volunteers for America, and private individuals, arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - General
    - Undated (Box-folder 2: 12)
    - 1980-1984 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - 1985 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - 1986 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - 1987 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - 1988 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - 1989 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Baltic, Bernard, 1985-1991 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - CATO, 1987 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Kerle, Gillam, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Letter drafts, 1985-1989, undated (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Letters received in prison, 1985 (Box-folder 3: 12-13, 4: 1)
  - Letters sent from prison, 1985 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Letters to editors, 1982-1989 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Libertarian Ballot Access Committee, 1979-1989 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Libertarian Finance Committee, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Libertarian National Committee, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Libertarian Party, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Libertarian Party News, 1986 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Libertarian Student Network, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Lindsay, Allen, 1985-1988, undated (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Paul Jacob Defense Fund, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 4: 11, 5: 1-2)
  - Paul, Ron, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Personal, 1984-1990 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Scream!, 1985 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Selective Service System, 1981-1990 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Speaking engagements, 1985-1990, undated (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - Tax Accountability Amendment Committee, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Volunteers for America, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - Welcome home letters, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - Winger, Richard, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Young Libertarian Alliance, 1978 (Box-folder 6: 7)
- Speeches and Writings, 1980-1989, undated
  Drafts, notes, and typescripts of speeches given by Paul Jacob. Also includes published and unpublished writings and personal statements, as well as transcripts of interviews. Arranged chronologically, then alphabetically thereunder.
  - Anti-draft writings, drafts, notes, and typescript, undated (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - "The Anti-war Demonstrations of the Sixties," typescript, undated (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Article for the Arkansas Gazette, notes and typescripts, undated (Box-folder 6: 10)
  - Interview of Paul Jacob by Frontlines, undated (Box-folder 6: 11)
  - "A Letter to the Libertarian National Convention,", undated (Box-folder 6: 12)
  - Libertarian Party move to Washington writings, typescript, undated (Box-folder 6: 13)
  - "The Major Patries Deserve Duke and LaRouche," Libertarian View, undated (Box-folder 6: 14)
  - "My Political Writings," holograph and typescript, undated (Box-folder 6: 15)
  - Response to The Covenant, the Sword and the Arm of the Lord, holograph, undated (Box-folder 6: 16)
  - Response to the War on Drugs, undated (Box-folder 6: 17)
  - Speech, New Hampshire, notes, undated (Box-folder 6: 18)
  - Speech, Ohio Libertarian Party convention, undated (Box-folder 6: 19)
  - Speech on the Selective Service System, Sherwood Kiwanis Club, undated (Box-folder 6: 20)
  - Speech, outlines, undated (Box-folder 6: 21)
  - Speech, untitled, undated (Box-folder 6: 22)
  - Speech, untitled introduction and afterword, undated (Box-folder 6: 23)
  - Speech, student aid for draft non-registrants, notes, undated (Box-folder 6: 24)
  - Unemployment writings, undated (Box-folder 6: 25)
  - Women's rights writings, undated (Box-folder 6: 26)
  - Letters to the editor, 1980-1989, undated (Box-folder 6: 27)
  - Anti-draft article, Liberty, 1981 (Box-folder 6: 28)
  - Lists of publications and speeches, 1981-1987, undated (Box-folder 6: 29)
  - Published draft registration opposition articles, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - "An Open Letter to N.O.W and All Feminists,", 1982 February 11 (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - Anti-draft article, LP News, 1982 September (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - Interview of Paul Jacob by KARN, radio broadcast transcript, 1982 September (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - Press release, 1982 October 25 (Box-folder 7: 5)
  - "The Draft Is Slavery," The Rainbow Cadenza, 1983 (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - Interview of Paul Jacob by Dianne Pilcher, Libertarian Vision, 1983 (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - Interview of Paul Jacob by Wendy McElroy, Caliber, 1983 (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - Interview of Paul Jacob by Peter Elloway, Free Texas, 1983 August (Box-folder 7: 9)
  - Press release, 1983 August 1 (Box-folder 7: 10)
  - Speech, Libertarian and War Conference, Los Angeles, 1984 March 31-April 1 (Box-folder 7: 11)
  - Interview of Paul Jacob by Jerry Markon, The Michigan Daily, 1985 February 6-7 (Box-folder 7: 12)
  - Press release, 1985 April 5 (Box-folder 7: 13)
  - Press release, 1985 May 1 (Box-folder 7: 14)
  - "S.S. Prosecutes Man Who Tried to Enlist,", 1986, undated (Box-folder 7: 15)
  - "With a Little Help from My Friends," monthly column drafts, 1986-1987, undated (Box-folder 7: 16)
  - Press release, 1986 January 19 (Box-folder 7: 17)
  - Speech, Libertarian National Committee, 1986 August (Box-folder 7: 18)
  - Interview of Paul Jacob by James W. Harris, Chic Magazine, 1986 October (Box-folder 7: 19)
  - Speech, introduction for Ron Paul, Young Americans for Freedom conference, Washington D.C., 1987 (Box-folder 7: 20)
  - "Ballot Access," notes and holograph, 1989, undated (Box-folder 7: 21)
  - Personal statement, 1989 July 15 (Box-folder 7: 22)
- Writings by Others, 1944-1987, undated
  Articles and other writings mainly related to Libertarianism and war, arranged alphabetically by author.
  - General, 1969-1984 (Box-folder 7: 23)
  - "A Program for Vietnam Veterans... and Everyone Else Who Should Care," WTTW/Chicago, broadcast transcript, 1986 (Box-folder 7: 24)
  - Assorted articles, The Journal of Libertarian Studies, 1977-1981 (Box-folder 7: 25)
  - Bandow. National Service: The Enduring Panacea, book outline, undated (Box-folder 7: 26)
  - Baxter, Rev. David M. "Why I Am Opposed to the Draft,", 1982 (Box-folder 7: 27)
  - Crane, Edward H. "America's Counterrevolution,", undated (Box-folder 7: 28)
  - Hart, B. H. Liddell. "Conscription," Why We Don't Learn from History, 1944 (Box-folder 7: 29)
  - Hayek, F. A. "Why I Am not a Conservative," The Constitution of Liberty, 1960 (Box-folder 7: 30)
  - Karp, Walter. "Republican Virtues,", 1979 (Box-folder 7: 31)
  - Lawson, Kay. "How State Laws Undermine Parties," Elections American Style, 1987 (Box-folder 7: 32)
  - Liggio, Leonard P. "Early Anti-Imperialism," Left and Right: A Journal of Libertarian Thought, 1966 (Box-folder 7: 33)
  - Liggio, Leonard P. "Isolationism, Old and New," Left and Right: A Journal of Libertarian Thought, 1966 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Liggio, Leonard P. "Palefaces or Redskins: A Profile of Americans," Left and Right: A Journal of Libertarian Thought, 1966 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Martin, James J. "A Look at Conscription, Then and Now,", undated (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Muskie, Edmun S. "The Draft: What Are the Alternatives?," Vital Speeches of the Day, 1969 (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - Paul, Ron. "The Scheming to Tighten the Bank Secrecy Act," Congressional Record, 1984 September 25 (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - Peck, M. Scott. "Mylai: An Examination of Group Evil," People of the Lie: The Hope for Healing Human Evil, 1983 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - Rothbard, Murray N. "America's Libertarian Revolution," Reason, 1976 (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - Rothbard, Murray N. "War and Foreign Policy," For a New Liberty: The Libertarian Manifesto, 1978 (Box-folder 8: 8)
  - Rothbard, Murray N. "War Collectivism in World War I," New History of Leviathan, 1972 (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - Schwartz, Peter. "Libertarianism: The Perversion of Liberty," The Intellectual Activist, 1986 (Box-folder 8: 10)
  - Smith, George H. "Will the Real Herbert Spencer Please Stand Up?," The Libertarian Review, 1978 (Box-folder 8: 11)
  - Webster, Daniel. "An Unpublished Speech," photocopy, undated (Box-folder 8: 12)
- Office Files, 1980-1991, undated
  Memoranda, reports, notes, and printed material relating to the Libertarian committees and anti-draft organizations Paul Jacob participated in. Arranged alphabetically by organization, then alphabetically by title.
  - CATO, 1987 (Box-folder 8: 13)
  - Libertarian Party, 1980-1991, undated
    - General, 1984-1989 (Box-folder 8: 14-16)
    - Arkansas state chair, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 8: 17)
    - Assorted campaign materials, 1980-1989 (Box-folder 9: 1-2, 19: 3)
    - Ballot Access Committee, 1988, undated (Box-folder 9: 3-7, 19: 4)
    - Citizens for Congressional Reform, 1988-1991 (Box-folder 10: 1)
    - Conventions, 1981-1991 (Box-folder 10: 2)
    - Finance Committee, 1987 (Box-folder 10: 3)
    - Mid-Atlantic workshop, 1981 (Box-folder 10: 4)
    - National Committee, 1981-1989 (Box-folder 10: 5)
    - Platform Committee, 1987, undated (Box-folder 10: 6)
    - Printed material, 1985-1989, undated (Box-folder 10: 7)
    - Ron Paul for president, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - Selective Service System, 1982-1987, undated (Box-folder 11: 2, 19: 5)
    - State parties, 1985-1991 (Box-folder 11: 3)
  - Notes, 1982-1989, undated
    - Undated (Box-folder 11: 4-6)
    - 1982-1989 (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - Paul Jacob Defense Fund, 1985, undated
    - General, 1985 (Box-folder 12: 2)
    - Anti-draft stickers, undated (Box-folder 12: 3)
  - Scream!, undated (Box-folder 12: 4)
  - Tax accountability amendment committee, 1990-1991, undated
    - General, 1990 (Box-folder 12: 5)
    - Printed material, 1990-1991, undated (Box-folder 12: 6)
  - Volunteers for America, 1985-1987, undated
    - General, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 12: 7)
    - Minuteman project, 1985, undated (Box-folder 12: 8)
- Printed Material, 1979-1991
  Clippings, flyers, newsletters, pamphlets, and periodicals related to the anti-draft movement of the 1980s and Libertarian ideology.
  - Clippings, 1975-1991, undated
    - Undated (Box-folder 12: 9-10)
    - 1975-1983 (Box-folder 13: 1)
    - 1984 (Box-folder 13: 2)
    - 1984-1989 (Box-folder 19: 6)
    - 1985 (Box-folder 13: 3-4)
    - 1986 (Box-folder 13: 5-6)
    - 1987 (Box-folder 13: 7, 14: 1-2)
    - 1988 (Box-folder 14: 3)
    - 1989 (Box-folder 14: 4)
    - 1990-1991 (Box-folder 14: 5)
  - Flyers, 1981-1984, undated
    - General, 1981-1984, undated (Box-folder 14: 6)
    - Anti-draft registration, 1984, undated (Box-folder 14: 7)
  - Newsletters, 1979-1991
    - General, 1981-1988 (Box-folder 14: 8)
    - Amnesty International Newsletter, 1987 (Box-folder 14: 9)
    - Association for a Volunteer Army, undated (Box-folder 14: 10)
    - Assorted student publications, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 14: 11)
    - Ballot Access News, 1989 (Box-folder 15: 1)
    - Board-O-Gram, 1986 (Box-folder 15: 2)
    - Free Marin, 1986 (Box-folder 15: 3)
    - Frontlines, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 15: 4)
    - Individual Liberty, 1981-1987 (Box-folder 15: 5)
    - Libertarian Party of Alabama, 1987 (Box-folder 15: 6)
    - Libertarian Party of Alaska, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 15: 7)
    - Libertarian Party of Arizona, 1984 (Box-folder 15: 8)
    - Libertarian Party of Arkansas, 1979-1983 (Box-folder 15: 9)
    - Libertarian Party of California, 1979-1987 (Box-folder 15: 10)
    - Libertarian Party of Canada, 1980, 1984 (Box-folder 15: 11)
    - Libertarian Party of Colorado, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 15: 12)
    - Libertarian Party of Connecticut, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 15: 13)
    - Libertarian Party of Georgia, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 15: 14)
    - Libertarian Party of Hawaii, 1979 (Box-folder 15: 15)
    - Libertarian Party of Illinois, 1980-1981, 1990 (Box-folder 15: 16)
    - Libertarian Party of Louisiana, 1984, 1989 (Box-folder 15: 17)
    - Libertarian Party of Massachusetts, 1986, 1989 (Box-folder 15: 18)
    - Libertarian Party of Maryland, 1980, 1987 (Box-folder 15: 19)
    - Libertarian Party of Michigan, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 15: 20)
    - Libertarian Party of Missouri, 1987 (Box-folder 15: 21)
    - Libertarian Party of New Hampshire, 1989 (Box-folder 15: 22)
    - Libertarian Party of New Jersey, 1987 (Box-folder 15: 23)
    - Libertarian Party of New Mexico, 1987 (Box-folder 15: 24)
    - Libertarian Party of New York, 1981-1986, 1988 (Box-folder 15: 25)
    - Libertarian Party of Ohio, 1986-1987, undated (Box-folder 16: 1)
    - Libertarian Party of Pennsylvania, 1981, 1986 (Box-folder 16: 2)
    - Libertarian Party of South Carolina, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 16: 3)
    - Libertarian Party of Texas, 1984, 1986 (Box-folder 16: 4)
    - Libertarian Party of Utah, 1985 (Box-folder 16: 5)
    - Libertarian Party of Virginia, 1980-1989 (Box-folder 16: 6)
    - Libertarian Vanguard, 1982 (Box-folder 16: 7)
    - Liberty Pledge, 1986-1991 (Box-folder 16: 8)
    - Taxnews, 1990 (Box-folder 16: 9)
    - The Familist, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 16: 10)
    - The Liberator, 1987 (Box-folder 16: 11)
    - The Reporter, 1984, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 16: 12)
    - Resistance, 1984-1985, undated (Box-folder 16: 13)
    - Ron Paul's presidential campaign, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 16: 14)
  - Pamphlets, 1983, undated
    - General, undated (Box-folder 16: 15)
    - Anti-draft registration, 1983, undated (Box-folder 16: 16)
  - Periodicals, 1979-1991
    - General, 1979-1984, undated (Box-folder 16: 17)
    - General, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 17: 1)
    - American Libertarian, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 17: 2)
    - CATO Byline, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 17: 3)
    - CATO Policy Analysis, 1980-1989 (Box-folder 17: 4)
    - CATO Policy Report, 1986, 1989 (Box-folder 17: 5)
    - The Citizen's Claw, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 17: 6)
    - Citizens Rule Book, undated (Box-folder 17: 7)
    - Crossroads: Term Limitation Today, 1991 (Box-folder 17: 8)
    - Exegesis, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 17: 9)
    - Final Draft, 1987 (Box-folder 17: 10)
    - Freedom Network News, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 17: 11)
    - Free Norma Jean, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 17: 12)
    - Free World Chronicle, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 17: 13)
    - Index on Liberty, 1987 (Box-folder 17: 14)
    - Journal of Civil Defense, 1986 (Box-folder 17: 15)
    - The Justice Times, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 17: 16)
    - Laissez Faire Books, 1983, 1987 (Box-folder 18: 1)
    - Liberty Today, 1989 (Box-folder 18: 2)
    - Nomos, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 18: 3)
    - The Objector, 1982 (Box-folder 18: 4)
    - The Officer, 1987 (Box-folder 18: 5)
    - Recon, 1985, undated (Box-folder 18: 6)
    - Resistance News, 1981-1987 (Box-folder 18: 7)
    - Scream!, 1984 (Box-folder 18: 8)
    - University publications, 1982-1990 (Box-folder 18: 9)
    - The Voluntaryist, 1983,1985 (Box-folder 18: 10)
- Videorecordings, 1982, undated (Box 20)
  3 VHS videocassettes and 1 Betamax videocassette
  - "Image," Ron Paul, undated
  - "Volunteers for America," Paul Jacob, undated
  - "We Hold These Truths," Libertarian Party, 1982 January 1
- Sound Recordings, 1981-1985, undated (Box 20)
  5 compact sound cassettes
  - "Defense Debate: Ronald Reagan vs Walter Mondale,", 1984 October 21
  - Let Freedom Rock, Captain Flashback, 1985
  - "Radio Interview of Paul Jacob,", 1981 January
  - Songs of Liberty: Music of the Revolutionary War, The Colonial Williamsburg Foundation, undated
  - "Speech and Questions at The State University of New York at Binghamton,", 1982 March 2
- Memorabilia, 1989, undated
  Eight nametags, sixteen pins, two t-shirts, one ribbon, and one cocktail napkin.
  - Ribbon and cocktail napkin, undated (Box-folder 18: 11)
  - Assorted "Paul Jacob" name tags, 1989, undated (Box 21)
  - Assorted pins, 1989, undated (Box 21)
  - "Free Paul Jacob" t-shirts, undated (Box 22)